Michael, welcome to my channel. Today we are going to speak
about float and double and how these two major abstractions
and implementations affect other programmers' lives. So,
please, introduce yourself. Thank you. It's very
nice to be here. Thank you for inviting me, Nikita. My name is
Michael Overton. I'm a professor of computer science and
math at NYU, New York University in New York. I've been there
my whole career. And it's not my primary interest, but one of
my interests has been floating-point arithmetic for a long
time, mainly because I got into that because I was teaching
numerical computing in the computer science department,
and I was really interested in explaining to the students
much more about how the computing worked instead of The
typical thing in a numerical analysis class in the math
department is you spend about 15 minutes talking about
that, and then you talk about all these mathematical
methods. But actually, the details of the computing are
very interesting, especially to computer science
students. So I ended up writing notes, and then that turned
into a small book that I wrote that was published for SIAM,
Society for Industrial Applied Math, in 2001. And then,
well, I left that book. I mean, I used the book over many years
but didn't really look back at it much over the last 20 years
until recently I had the opportunity to write a second
edition because so much has changed since 2001. Yeah, that
you won't know yet. So much has changed since 2001. The basic
principles are the same, but technology, of course, has
totally changed. And so I'm actually pretty close to
finishing the second edition, which will be published by
SIAM, well, presumably in 2025. Oh, great news. Can you
please explain a little bit for the audience, what did
exactly change? Maybe it would be better to first explain
what happened in 1985 with the original floating point
standard. If we go back further in history, and then we'll
come back to the present later, if you go all the way back,
floating point was actually first developed by Konrad Zuse
during World War II in Germany. He actually built a binary
floating-point arithmetic computer. It wasn't
electronic, though. It was electromechanical. And then
later, the first electronic computers were developed.
There were a lot of people, of course, who were involved in
this whole process post-war, particularly von Neumann and
Turing. And then various companies, of course, started
building electronic computers and marketing them,
particularly IBM. There were all these different ways of
doing computer arithmetic. It was very confusing because
you might run a program, say Fortran in those days, a Fortran
program on one computer, an IBM computer, and you might get
quite different results from if you ran it on another
computer because the way the arithmetic was implemented on
the computer was quite different. There were a lot of people
who were concerned about this. The The floating point
standard was finally published in 1985 after about five
years of work. This was back actually soon after I was a grad
student. I wasn't involved in that, but some of my
colleagues and close friends were, and particularly
Professor Velvel Kahan of Berkeley, who led the whole
process. He was also involved in designing the
floating-point chip for the new, at that time, new Intel
8087, which was the floating-point chip. It was actually a
floating-point coprocessor that worked along with the
8088 that they were developing. And Kahan was heavily
involved in the design of that, and a lot of the same ideas
were adopted by the Standard, which was published in 1985 by
IEEE, and then adopted internationally as well. And so what
happened was that the Standard had an enormous impact,
because at the time, there were various so-called
mainframe computers, VAX, DECVAX, HP, IBM, I already
mentioned various others. Many of those names have gone
now. They were all doing their own thing. None of them really
wanted to change what they were doing. But then what
happened was that the personal computers took off like
crazy, particularly with the Intel chips, which were
adopted by IBM and the IBM PC. And then all the other
manufacturers of microprocessor chips that were used in
PCs, particularly Motorola, they all adopted the same
standard, with the same standard arithmetic. And
eventually the mainframes all faded away, like the big IBM
machines, which totally dominated computing in the 60s and
70s. People weren't using them so much anymore. People
were much more using the new Intel chips, and that continued
to develop over the years. So the standard was hugely
successful. The industry really adopted the changes. But
in terms of what's happened since, Well, the main
principles of the standard, which I can explain more about
later, are still pretty much widely adopted. But those are
the 32-bit and the 64-bit floating-point words, the single
and double formats. And what's happened most recently is
that with the massive amount of computing required by
machine learning, the various companies manufacturing
the chips used by machine learning, including Google and
NVIDIA particularly, they've started to use these shorter
formats, 16-bit and even 8-bit, and now even 4-bit floating
point format, which is completely Well, inaccurate. It's a
sea change. Very inaccurate. Yes. Scary, one might say. We
could talk more about that later, but yeah, back to you. So
yeah, thanks a lot for this very brief and deep introduction
to the floating point history. And you mentioned that
basically IEEE standard had a huge impact on the industry.
And why exactly this standard won the race among many
others? Well, it was the only standard, actually. What
happened was that there were all these different
manufacturers doing their own thing, and the standard
said, no, let's all do this. And there wasn't any competing
standard. And as I said, because of the phenomenal growth of
the PC industry and the chips that were used, excuse me, in
that industry, particularly the Intel chips and the
Motorola chips, they just all adopted the standard. They
all agreed, hey, this is a good thing. Then people's
programs will run as expected on different machines. And so
there wasn't actually a competing standard. What there
was, was there was a lot of debate in the committee, which
included academic computer scientists led by Kahan, and
also a lot of industry people from all the big names in
industry at the time, IBM, HP, and so forth, DEC. And they all
argued, of course, they didn't all agree on what should be
done at first. But Kahan's viewpoint was, well, very
forceful, but also very well grounded in sort of theory and
common sense. And also another thing that helped a lot, I
think, is that Kahan is a professor of computer science and
mathematics, I think, both at Berkeley. But also he came
from Toronto, where he had actually a lot of training in EE,
electrical engineering, as well. So he knew what he was
talking about when he began, when he talked about, you know,
hardware. He wasn't some guy who didn't know any of that
stuff. In brief, they listened to him. I think that the
standard has a lot of great stuff inside. But I want to also
highlight some problems that might be hidden in this
standard. Do you have any existing examples? For example,
in your book, you mentioned that gradual underflow is the
most controversial part of the standard. It was, but one
thing that's changed is that it's no longer controversial.
It's pretty much been adopted in hardware. What happened
was that in order to—well, maybe we should explain first for
our listeners what gradual underflow is. In a floating
point format, you only have, let's say, 32 bits. Let's
explain first how, before we get into underflow, let's
explain how these 32 bits are used. So there's one bit that's
needed for the sign of the number, plus or minus. So now
you're down to 31. Now, the format they agreed to adopt for
various reasons used the next eight bits to represent the
exponent in the floating point. So a floating point is a
system sometimes compared with scientific notation,
where you have, let's say, the simplest example, let's say,
Let's take the number 16. 16 is 2 to the power of 4. Well, in
binary, because we always use binary in floating point,
that's another story. There is actually decimal point,
decimal floating point two, that is used in business. But
scientifically, in scientific applications, by far the
majority of applications, it's binary floating point
that's used. And so the number 16 in binary is 1.0000, et
cetera, as many zeros as you want, times 2 to the power of 4,
16. 16 is 2 times 2 times 2 times 2, 16. So the 4 is stored in the
exponent field of the 32-bit word. that you have up to 8 bits,
so you can go up to about an exponent of something like 127,
because you have to allow for negative exponents as well.
And then the remaining 23 bits in the word, right, because
there are 32 but we've used 1 to the sine, 8 for the exponent,
that's for the so-called significand. So in the case of 16,
because it's the exact power of 2, it's just 1.000 and then a
bunch of zeros. But a more complicated number like pi, of
course, or even something like, say, almost any number
really, is not going to be 1.000, but it's going to be, you
know, it's going to have a bunch of ones and zeros in the
expansion. So you have 23 bits for this significand, plus
another bit that's so-called hidden, but let's leave that
aside for the moment. And then you've got these eight bits
for the exponent. And the exponent, as I said, it ranges from
basically from something like minus 127 to plus 127.
There's a couple of special exponents to represent special
numbers like zero and infinity, which is another interesting
number. But the business of the gradual underflow is what
happens when a number gets down to 2 to the minus 126, I think
it is, below that, you might say, well, look, we can't store a
number that's smaller than that, so we're going to have to
drop it down to zero. That would be not gradual underflow,
but abrupt underflow. But gradual underflow says, well,
no, actually, by being a bit more clever, we can actually
store 2 to the minus 127, 2 to the minus 128, all the way down to
It's actually 2 to the minus 149 in so-called single
precision, the 32-bit format. And that's what gradual
underflow is. Now, as I said, it was controversial because
implementing arithmetic with numbers that might be
so-called subnormal, that means they've dropped below
that underflow threshold down into the subnormal range
using gradual underflow, using having arithmetic that
works for those kinds of numbers as well as the ordinary
floating point numbers, the normalized ones. well, it's
more expensive, more complicated, and many of the
manufacturers just didn't want to do it. DEC, in
particular, was quite opposed to it. But Intel was highly in
favor, because of Kahan's influence, probably. But
eventually, everybody realized, okay, well, they were
allowed to do it in software to conform with the standard,
but that was a problem, because then the machines would
really, then the computations would really slow down. So
eventually, pretty much everyone adopted the hardware
gradual underflow. So that's actually not controversial
anymore, but it was back then. So that's one of the things
that's changed for the better. Maybe there are some other
examples. Well, the biggest one right now is this short
format thing for machine learning. Can you tell a little bit
more about that, please? Sure. So the standard defines
several floating point formats. 32-bit format, which is a
so-called single precision. In C that would be called
float. The 64-bit double format, double precision, in C
that would be called double. I think in Python it's called
float, right? This is what you're apparently interested
in. Because Python, at least the original Python anyway,
works just with the double precision 64-bit floating point
numbers. As I understand, please correct me if I'm wrong.
Yeah, that's correct. Yeah. OK, so then what about longer,
what about shorter formats? Well, in the 1985 format, 1985
standard, they only introduced single and double, and they
said to be conformant with the standard, you have to
implement single. And you can implement double, too, if you
want. And they recommended an extended format, but that's
not so interesting. So the standard is supposed to be
revised every 10 years, because if it isn't, it expires.
That's an IEEE rule. So that means it should have been
revised in 2005. Actually, the revision finally appeared
in 2008 after a lot of discussion. There were quite a lot of
changes in 2008. So they introduced a 128-bit format, which
is sometimes called quadruple precision. You've got
single, double, quadruple, 32, 64, 128. And they also
introduce half-precision, which is 16-bit. But that's
getting kind of short, because you still need one bit for the
sign. Now you have, I think, in the IEEE half-precision, you
have five bits for the exponent, which means the exponent
can only go up to 2 to the 16, right, from 2 to the minus 16 to 2 to
the plus 16, roughly. I think that leaves 10 bits for the
significand, plus one bit that's so-called hidden, which
is in every number except zero. OK, so a 16-bit format was
introduced. So that's called half-precision, usually, or
the number, the names were also changed. So in 2008, instead
of single and double, they started calling it binary 32 and
binary 64. Often that's abbreviated to FP32 or FP64. And
then binary 128 and binary 16, or BF16, I mean FP16. But And
then in 2019, there was another revision, again, slightly
late, one year late, but that wasn't a major revision. It
introduced a few new things and fixed a couple of bugs, but it
wasn't super major. But meanwhile, there was a big change
between 2008 and 2016, and that's that machine learning
took off. And what happened is it was Google first that said,
OK, well, let's do… Well, it wasn't only Google. A bunch of
people working in machine learning were saying, hey, let's
use 16-bit format because when you're saying multiplying
two 16-bit numbers, it's much It's a process that requires
much less power than multiplying 32-bit numbers. And so you
save power and you save space by having shorter formats.
That wasn't so much of an issue before machine learning came
along. But what's happened with machine learning is
there's just enormous amounts of computation involved.
And the reason that machine learning has suddenly been so
successful is because that's now possible with the
technology. It used to be that you couldn't do these kinds of
massive computations. It was just much too expensive. but
with computers becoming faster and faster and cheaper and
cheaper, now you can. The whole idea of neural nets, which
was promoted by Yann LeCun and others back even before the
turn of the century, I think, he was sort of speaking, you
know, he was sort of not quite alone in the wilderness, but
people weren't convinced that neural nets could ever work.
And then by about 2010 or so, it became very clear they were
amazingly effective. And by 2015 or 16, companies like
Google, who were developing their TPU, the Tensor
Processing Unit, realized that, okay, if we use 16-bit,
that's going to be much faster and cheaper. But in fact,
let's introduce a new format, they said, because they
didn't like binary 16 because the exponent range is so small
from 2 to the minus 16 to 2 to the 16. So what they introduced
was something that they called bfloat16. B stands for
brain, Google brain. And in that format, you have one bit for
the sign still. But now you have eight bits for the exponent,
which is the same as with IEEE single precision. And then,
OK, so that uses up nine of your 16 bits. And so what have you
got left? You've got seven left now, plus one hidden bit,
which is not even enough to represent more than two decimal
digits of accuracy. That might not be so obvious, but we
could talk about that later if that's of interest. People
were a little shocked that there's so little accuracy in the
numbers, but they said, look, hey, this is machine
learning. We're doing massive amounts of it, and there's
tons of redundancy, and we don't need high accuracy. You
can't argue with the fact that machine learning has been
enormously successful, so it apparently works. You
wouldn't want to be doing that for scientific problems that
require highly accurate computations. But in machine
learning, it seems that's not necessary. So they
introduced BFLOAT16, they built their own chips. They were
not exactly secretive about it. They did publish this. And
then other manufacturers started following the same
format, including NVIDIA and Intel, which I guess is the two
biggest players making chips at this point. Well, maybe one
or two others, but anyway, those are certainly two very
major ones. So that's fine. Then people said, well, look, if
16 bits, why not 8 bits? So a bunch of researchers started
using 8 bits, first just simulating it because they didn't
have 8-bit hardware. But then again, the manufacturers
started building the 8-bit hardware. So both Intel and
NVIDIA anNaNced 8-bit floating-point chips. Well,
that's getting really short. And now the latest thing is
just a few months ago, I think it was in April or so, NVIDIA
announced that they're making 4-bit floating point, which
is kind of shocking. I mean, that's one bit. I don't know how
to even imagine their binary layout. So the first bit is
obviously for sign, then two bits, I guess, is for exponent
and one bit for mantissa. Yeah, mantissa is another word for
significand. That's fine, just for our audience. Yeah,
that's right, plus the one hidden bit, which gives you two
bits for the significand. I'm actually not sure if it's
that. That's probably right, or maybe it's one less bit for
the exponent. I'm not sure. I didn't look it up yet. I'm
planning to do that very soon. Anyway, where's the limit?
Yeah, that's quite interesting. You've also mentioned
that hidden bit quite a lot. So can you please explain what hidden bit is?
Every number, every binary,
every number except for zero has a leading one, right?
Because you can always, the whole point
of floating point
is you normalize, you shift the binary point so that it floats
to the position. That's why it's called floating point. It
floats to the position where the one is in front before the
binary point and then zero, zero, zero.
Well, the thing is, all numbers,
whether it's pi or the square root of two or one-tenth,
One-tenth is an interesting one. Let's do that one.
One-tenth is 1.100110011001100 dot dot dot times 2 to the
minus 4, if I'm remembering correctly. I have to use a
calculator for that. That's one-tenth as it turns out.
Okay. Roughly one-tenth, yeah. Yeah, exactly, if you go on
forever. But again, you see, it starts with a 1. Well, of
course, it starts with a 1, because I floated the binary
point so that there would be a 1 in the front. I didn't put
0.0001100. I could have done, but the whole point of
floating point is you want to float that binary point to get
the one in front, and then you have times a power. But that one
in front, why do we need to store it? We know it's a one, so
that's the hidden bit. Now, before the standard, actually
it was Vax who first started doing this, the DEC-VAX, but
before the DEC-VAX, People did store it, and the reason is
they needed a way to write zero. And zero is 0.000. You can't
float the binary point for zero to get a one in front. There is
no one. It's all zeros. But you see, you can represent zero
instead through a special exponent. So going back again to
the 32-bit format, I said the numbers, the exponents are
something like minus 126 to plus 127, but that leaves a
couple of numbers free, and the number which corresponds to
minus 127 corresponds to the zero. number, and at the other
end of the range, the exponent 128, I think it is, or maybe
it's 127, corresponds to infinity. Because in IEEE
arithmetic, one divided by zero is infinity. Yeah. But this
is a very interesting part. Some languages treat this as
infinity, but some languages do rise an exception. For
example, CPython does that. It rises zero division
exception for this case. So how do you feel about this little
misinterpretation of the standard? Well, that's a very
good question. I don't think that is a misinterpretation.
The point is that the number becomes infinity, but
according to the standard, an exception, when you divide by
zero, that's an exception. This is a divide by zero
exception. What's happening in CPython then is that
CPython is trapping the exception and saying, OK, stop. The
exception is thrown by the chip. There are various
exceptions in floating point. One of them is division by
zero. Another one is overflow, where you make the number so
big that it no longer fits. Another one is underflow, where
you make it so small that it no longer fits, even after
running through all. Actually, the underflow flag is
tremendously complicated because it's set, I think, even
when you go into the gradual underflow range. You'd have to
look at my book, especially the second edition, to get all
this clear. We'll put a link into the description. Yeah, I
don't have the second edition ready yet, but I will send you a
copy as soon as it's ready. Oh, thank you. Awesome. But it
will be published by SIAM, hopefully in 2025. I'm getting
pretty close. Yeah, so there's five exceptions. Divide by
0, overflow, underflow. Another interesting one is
invalid operation. So, zero over zero is an invalid operation and
generates a NaN, which is not a number. which is another
special pattern in the floating point using the maximum
possible exponent. So again, probably CPython would trap
that and stop, I guess, right? But isn't there a way to set the
compiler so that it runs with infinities and nans or not? I
don't think so. There might be some hidden undocumented
flag, something like that, but I don't think there is a
documented way to do that. I'm surprised about that because
there certainly is in C. And in the C stats, it took C and also
Fortran a long time to catch up with the standard, even
though C had a major revision in 1999, which was long after
the standard was published, 14 years after. It didn't even
mention it really, or may have mentioned it, but it didn't do
anything much with it. I'm sorry, I'm getting that wrong.
That was 1989. In 1999, they finally did catch up with the
standard, and they made a lot of changes. The expert, the big
expert on floating point in C is Nelson Beebe actually. So in C,
the normal default behavior is that you do generate
infinities and NaNs. And this allows you to do something
like, there's this one example I like is the parallel
resistance formula. So if you have, two resistors in
parallel. This is something that goes back to high school.
You have this example in your book. Yes, exactly. There's
the example. The parallel resistance formula is where you
have two resistors hooked up in parallel on a circuit: 1/(1/R1 + 1/R2)
And one of the resistors has resistance R1 and the other one R2.
And that's the formula for the total resistor. So if they're
the same, if R1 and R2 are both 1, then you get 1 over 2. So the
result is a half, because half the current goes one way and
half the current goes the other way. So that makes sense.
But what if R1 is very small? Well, then you see most of the
current goes through the resistor R1, and then the total
resistance is 1 over 1 over R1 plus a little bit more, which is
only a little bit less than R1 because most of the current
goes through R1 when R1 is much less than R2. But what if R1 is
zero? Well, if you plug R1 equals zero into that formula, you
don't allow infinities, and then it doesn't work. But if you
do allow infinities, you get 1 over R1 is infinity. 1 over R2
is, say, 1. 1 plus infinity is infinity. And then 1 over
infinity is 0. So all the current goes through R1. There's no
resistance in the circuit. So it makes valid scientific
sense. Now, of course, most people are not computing with
parallel circuits. But there's a lot of examples like this.
And it's actually a very useful thing to have. So I'm pretty
surprised that CPython doesn't allow that. Pretty much all
the other languages I know do. MATLAB, certainly. I will
have to double-check that right now, because I now begin to
doubt myself. It may be that it's a setting you have to
choose. I've double-checked this right now. So you cannot
configure CPython not to rise this error. I guess the main
motivation for that is because Python tries to be very
user-friendly, and I can see a lot of use cases where
Infinity is not very user-friendly. Do you agree with that?
I think it's something that's, yeah, a lot of people have
different opinions about it. It's, yeah, certainly if you,
I mean, Infinity makes sense, but of course NaNs really
don't. NaNs are basically telling you, look, it doesn't
make any sense. What people sometimes use NaNs for is
initializing data and then the data that's supposed to be
then set to other values, and if something is still a NaN at
the end, you know something's wrong. It's called signal and
NaN as far as I know. There's two kinds of NaNs, there's
signaling NaNs and quiet NaNs, and the difference is kind of
complicated. I can tell you a bit if you're interested about
the what's going on with the, let's see, did we finish up with
the exception? Maybe I'll just reiterate about the
exceptions. Yeah, so there's five exceptions. There's
division by zero, overflow, underflow, invalid
operation, which is something like zero over zero, or the
square root of minus one would be another invalid
operation, unless you're in some kind of mode like MATLAB
where you allow complex numbers. And then also another
example of an invalid operation would be infinity minus
infinity, because it doesn't make sense, you know, which
one is bigger. Infinity plus infinity is infinity. The
fifth exception is when the result of a computation is not
exact, an exact floating point number. But that's kind of a
misnomer to call that an exception, because actually
that's what happens almost all the time. But anyway, it's
still called an exception for some reason. And so there's a
flag for that too. But that's another big thing that's
changed is that this whole business with flags, you see, it
used to be that setting flags was a good thing to do. And then,
you know, the compiler can, the runtime, the runtime
process can check the flags and so forth. But now with all
these much more complicated things like multi-threading
and so on, flags can actually kind of get in the way. This is
really beyond my expertise. I'm not a computer designer.
But from what I've heard, there's not so much not so much
enthusiasm for setting and checking these exception flags
anymore. But that may not be the case with CPython. It sounds
like maybe it's not. So what's going on with the floating
point? Well, with the 8-bit floating point, What's
happened is that there's now a new IEEE committee called
Committee P3109. The original IEEE committee, the
floating part committee, was called IEEE P754. And you hear
all the time about 754 arithmetic, IEEE 754. anybody knows
much about floating point has heard about 754. It just means
the IEEE floating point standard. So that was 1985. I guess
they've been numbering them sequentially. So now we're up
to 3,109 for these working groups of the IEEE. But not very
many of them, of course, have to do with floating point. IEEE
is a huge organization. So 3109 is a committee that was set up
to define, to make recommendations for standardizing
8-bit floating point. And so I was contacting these people
to find out more about it. And they said, well, look, why
don't you just join the committee? And so I did. And
actually, it's been extremely interesting. Oh, I didn't
know that. Yeah, yeah. No, you wouldn't because that fact
hasn't been published. But the 3109 committee has now
published an interim report, which I was involved in in a
tiny way, along with all the other committee members. The
leaders of the committee, there are several leaders,
secretary. Well, that's not getting into the
personalities. But anyway, there's lots of very, very
competent people, of course, they're mostly machine
learning experts. But there's also floating point
experts. Well, of course, some of them are experts on both. I
don't know much about machine learning, but so I'm in there
from the floating point side. But there's also a bunch of
hardware people like people from Intel and Actually, I
don't know if there's anybody from NVIDIA on the committee,
but definitely there is from Intel and other companies. And
so the P3109 committee has published an interim report.
Now, it's not clear how much impact the 3109
recommendations are going to have compared with the 754
recommendations. because the industry is moving very fast
and the companies are not waiting around to see what the
committee does. Maybe we'll become standardized
following the committee recommendations. I guess that's
what we hope. The recommendations right now are that with
only eight bids, you have to be a little more well, you have to
be very thoughtful about what you're going to use them for.
Now, going back to the 32-bit and 64-bit IEEE, the original
single and double floating point formats, which are ones
that are mostly used. So those ones, as I said, there's
special representations for infinity, also minus
infinity, zero, but also minus zero, which is another
complication that was also kind of controversial, because
if you're going to have 1 over infinity is 0, well then
shouldn't 1 over minus infinity be minus 0? And anyway, if
you're going to represent 0, you've got to do something with
a sign bit, so why should it always be the positive sign bit?
Why not negative? So there's actually two representations
for zero in the original IEEE format. So there's zero and
there's minus zero. But then this leads to some very
interesting unexpected behaviors because is zero equal to
minus zero? If you check that in a programming language like
Python. Yeah, it is. It is, that's right. Sorry, this wasn't
meant to be an exam question, but you're exactly right. But
on the other hand, is infinity equal to minus infinity?
Well, absolutely not. They're very different. So that
means that A can be equal to B, but 1 over A not equal to 1 over B,
where A and B are 0 and minus 0. So that's kind of
disconcerting, to say the least. But really, the choice of
having minus infinity really leads one to having minus 0.
And if you're going to have 1 over 0 is infinity, then you
really you're kind of stuck with the idea of if you're going
to have two infinities, you're going to need to have two
zeros also. Well, P3109 discussed all this. This was
actually before I joined the committee. And the decision
they made was, or we made, I suppose, although I wasn't
involved in the beginning, for better or for worse, there's
only going to be one zero, no minus zero in the
recommendations. And Also, there's multiple NaNs in
IEEE. As you pointed out, there's signaling NaNs and quiet
NaNs. And it's actually a lot of different NaNs, because
what you can do is you have all these extra bits you're not
using anyway from the significand field corresponding to
the special exponent field for the NaN. And so you might as
well use them to code the origin of the NaN. So there's a lot
of different NaNs in IEEE. you can't test whether one is
equal to another. A NaN is never equal to anything, even to
itself. But they can still be, the bit patterns can still be
examined. Okay, well, 3109 in the 8-bit format decided, no,
we don't want so many NaNs. We can't afford the space. So
there's only gonna be one NaN also. And they're using the
bit pattern that normally would be used for minus zero to
represent NaNs. So that means you've got one zero, one
NaN. Now, what about the infinities? two infinities, but
one over zero is not infinity, because if it was, and then, if
it was, and then you took one over infinity, that would give
you zero, but one over minus infinity would also give you
zero, and then you took one over that, and you'd get plus
infinity, that really leads to confusion. So the
recommendation right now, I don't think this has been
published yet in the interim report, but probably what is
gonna be recommended is that one over zero is NaN, not
infinity. Oh. So that's the current proposal. It hasn't
been voted on yet, I don't think. What's your opinion on
that? Because from the mathematical standpoint, I guess
they both do not and do make sense at the same time. Well, I
think my opinion is the committee is right that if you're not
going to have minus zero, and you are going to have plus or
minus infinity, then you should not say that 1 over is plus
infinity, because it's too confusing. Just to reiterate
what I just said a moment ago, because I went very fast. If you
have minus infinity, 1 over minus infinity would be 0, and
then 1 over 0, if that's plus infinity, no, that's really
bad. Whereas in IEEE, 1 over minus infinity would be minus 0,
and then 1 over minus 0 would be minus infinity, so at least you
get it back. Then you might say, well, then what good are the
infinities? Well, the point of the infinities is to use them
when you get overflow. You can overflow to infinity or
underflow to zero, overflow to infinity or minus infinity,
depending on the sign. But then there's the question, a lot
of the machine learning people say that actually they don't
even want the numbers to overflow to infinity because they
want to use what they call saturation arithmetic because
otherwise they're going to see a lot of infinities with only
eight bits because it's going to overflow a lot. It's
interesting because this discussion about how many bits to
have It takes you back also to discussions in the 1940s. In
the 1940s, von Neumann, who was the big player then, he
didn't want to even have exponent fields. He thought
significand fields are enough, the exponent fields can be
taken care of by the programmer. which we see back in the
1940s, computers were super expensive. You had very few
bits. And he basically wanted to get the programmer to do
everything that they, you know, to sort of not outsource
things from the programmer to the computation, which the
programmer could actually do. But now we're back to the same
kind of discussions with with machine learning, because if
you look at some of these papers on machine learning, they
say, well, in order to avoid overflow, we need to do scaling,
we need to scale the numbers properly, which basically
means that programmer intervention saying, look, before
you start doing a calculation, we should scale everything
by two to the something or other. To try to avoid overflow or
underflow. That's really complicated, but it seems from
what I see in the machine learning literature, this is
something that people are doing. And with saturation
arithmetic, they won't have to worry about things
overflowing to infinity, but then the trouble with
saturation arithmetic, what happens is, suppose you keep
doubling and you have a very large number and you multiply it
by itself, and you'll just get the same number back again,
because you already have the largest number. With IEEE, it
would go to infinity. And then if you divided that by that
large number again, it would still be infinity. So you'd
really know. But with this, if you have a very large number,
and now you start making it smaller again, you'll never
really know how big it was. You really lost not just
precision, but the scaling. And so again, it seems a little
scary. Of course, another big issue is that machine
learning, it's not just being used to detect cats from dogs
anymore. I mean, that's the stereotype, right? It's being
used for everything. And so there's a lot of risk in doing
that that are not sufficiently accurate. So it's very hard
to see how all this will play out. And with P3109, I'm sure
that we will come up with it showing a report eventually. But
whether the industry will have already moved on so far that
they won't be interested, I don't know. Or maybe it'll be in
step with what the industry is doing. It's hard to tell.
Another thing that's happening is that 754, the original
floating point standard, is they're already gearing up for
the next revision, because it was 1985 and 2008 late, then
2019 late. So the next one's supposed to come out in 2029,
which is, you know, getting scarily close. It's only five
years away. And this floating point standard is a very
complex document, and a lot of things are changing in terms
of the details of the hardware and stuff. And so I was also
joining discussions. The whole 3109 committee was
invited to join discussions about setting up the new 2029
754 working group. That's being led by a guy called Leonard
Tsai, who's very on the ball. And that committee will be set
up very soon. The working group, I say committee, but the
IEEE nomenclature is working group. Groups are the
technical, are the committees basically that make all
these technical recommendations on all sorts of things to
the IEEE, you know, approval mechanism, whatever it is, the
board or whatever. I also have one last question, but I think
it is a very big one, so feel free to answer as short or as long
as you want. I think that we haven't discussed any chips,
really. So do you think that any modern architectures are
better than others in terms of floating-point
computations? Or maybe there are some special
instructions or special architecture designs? Yeah, I
agree with you. It's a big question. I'm not really the right
person to ask because I'm not a hardware expert. But I mean,
in general, the Intel chips have been very high quality.
They've been very consistent about adopting the standard.
If you look at the Mac, look at Macintosh computers as they
used to be called, they used to use Motorola chips and they
switched to Intel chips. Now they have their own chips, the
Apple system on a chip. That's the M1, M2, M3. I think they're
M4. They already announced M4, yeah. So those chips are also
very good, I believe. They are very careful about
implementing the standard properly. Actually, there's an
interesting story that we might talk about the Pentium bug,
but let me come back to that. NVIDIA NVIDIA became a big
player in this business through gaming, right, through
GPUs. And the original GPUs were not IEEE compliant. But
then they really switched with CUDA. They really started
making things IEEE compliant. I think they don't have the, I
believe they do not include the exception flags for the
reasons that I kind of alluded to earlier, because it's not
so convenient with multi-threading and stuff, and all this
parallelism. But in most things, they're IEEE compliant.
Yeah, the Google chips, I'm not so sure, because those are
doing bfloat16. But as far as I know, they don't even have
gradual underflow. I might be wrong about that. I don't
think they've stated whether they have or not. I've talked
to somebody at Google who's been super helpful. But there
are some things he said he couldn't tell me. And if you'd like
to hear the Pentium bug story, that's another one. Yeah, I
should there. Probably know it, yeah. So as I said, Intel
built all these great chips. Then in 1994, the Pentium was
the sort of new thing, I guess then. And Pentium since then
has undergone lots and lots of changes. It's become a brand
name of Intel. So there's many, many different kinds of
Pentium. But in 1994, your cat is in the picture. Oh, he's
also interested in floating points. Okay, so in 1994, there
was a guy called Nicely, Thomas Nicely, I think he was in
Virginia. He was a mathematician doing experiments with
number theory. And he was doing a lot of computations and
eventually realized that some of them weren't correct. So
actually the most important thing about the standard, I
didn't even really tell you. Maybe I should tell you that
first. So what the standard really states is that beyond all
these you know, details like infinities and the details of
the representation. The most important thing that the
standard set is that when you add two floating point
numbers, the result should be the correctly rounded value
of the true result. That means it's as accurate as possible
given the representation. Same thing with multiply,
divide, and so on. And it used to be like in the old Cray
supercomputers, they wouldn't bother with that. They
said, well, we just want to be fast. And if it's not quite
right, sometimes it doesn't really matter. Well, that was
very much the attitude that, you know, that kind of attitude
prompted the IEEE 754 committee in the first place, which
said, no, computations have to be accurate. I should have
said this earlier, because this is really like a crucial,
crucial point. But anyway, it's nice to save it for the end,
maybe. Well, that means in doubles, 64-bit, that the
significands have to be accurate to, I guess it's 53 bits,
the significands or mantissas, because you've got a bunch
of bits also for the exponent, 11 bits for the exponent. So
they need to be accurate to 53 bits in the significand,
including the hidden bit, which translates in decimal, if
you can sort of figure the translation. So log base 10 of 2 to
the 53, which is a number. So what is that? It's
approximately 16. So in other words, 2 to the 53 is
approximately 10 to the 16. That's just a little
mathematical fact. Why do we even use base 10 anyway? That's
another interesting thing, right? But it's because of
this, right? We have 10 fingers and thumbs, so that's
thousands of years old. People, you see that 10. Reckoning
in 10s idea. I have some history stuff in the book, too, if
you're interested in more. Anyway, as I said, binary is the
thing to use in computers, and that idea has been accepted
really since the 1940s. But if something is accurate to 53
bits, how many decimal digits is it accurate to? Well, the
answer is approximately 16, and that's the reason right
there. OK, so Nicely found that his numbers, which were
supposed to be accurate to about 16 digits, they were only
accurate to about four digits in some very unusual cases.
And he thought, well, this is weird. So he contacted Intel.
And it turned out Intel actually knew about it, but they
weren't telling anyone because they thought nobody would
notice. And then it was a huge thing in the media. But there is
always one guy. Exactly. And it was really amazing, because
if you had tried to convince the public through an
advertising campaign that it's really important to have 16
decimal digits, people are just going to yawn. But as soon as
you tell them that they can't have it, then they all of a
sudden wake up and say, no, we want them. And that's what
Intel said. They said, well, it's okay. Nobody really needs
this. And we'll fix your computer. We'll fix the
scientists' computers. But the everyday person using a PC,
they don't need this. It's really not necessary. And then
people were furious. No, we want it to. And so finally, Intel
had to backtrack and had to replace all those Pentium chips,
which, of course, cost them a lot of money. And it was very bad
press. But in the end, it was actually good for everybody, I
think, because now people realize that you really have to be
very careful about these things. There are much more
attention to proving that hardware implementations are
correct, this sort of thing. And there haven't been any
repeats about this. And it was so ironic because Intel had
done more than any company in history for bringing accurate
floating point to the masses, to people in general,
non-scientists and non-engineers. And all of a sudden,
they were getting bad press. But anyway, it came back and now
for years, there were these laptops saying Intel inside,
right? And that's very much appreciated that the Intel
chips are very good. If you look at the top 500, I couldn't
find anything more recent than, there should be something
from even this year and last year, but there's a Wikipedia
page for the top 500 PCs, processors from August 2022, which
is a long time ago. Based on flops. Yes, the fastest
computers. Of course, these are all massively parallel
processors. In 2022, I think it was like 380 out of 500 of them
were Intel, or at least they were x86. No, I think they're
almost all x86. I would have to check. And most of them are
Intel. The one company I haven't mentioned actually is AMD.
I knew there was another one. I was forgetting. AMD pretty
much makes all the same chips as Intel does because they
struck a deal with Intel way back in the 80s when IBM adopted
Intel. This is another super ironic story, right? IBM
adopted Intel to make their PC because they didn't think
that, to make the chip for their PC. In those days, they
didn't think that the laptops were going to be a serious
business. They had their big mainframe business where IBM,
big company, Intel is just this little startup thing. Of
course, now Intel is a far bigger company. And also, of
course, another small player back then was Bill Gates and
Microsoft, and they got the deal with Intel, and then, of
course, Microsoft became much bigger than IBM, too. So
these things, they're all very ironic, right? Well, the
reason that AMD got to make the same Intel designs was that
IBM said, look, we're not going to be just stuck with this
little company, Intel. What if Intel goes bankrupt? We need
a backup. So they insisted on a second company. This is all
documented in a book called, I think it's called, I forget. I
could look it up. It'll be in the second edition. not a book by
me. I mean, the book that describes these IBM decisions is
something published. Anyhow, so they insisted on another
company being able to sell these too. Well, so AMD was kind of
secondary to Intel for a long time, but then Intel really
stumbled in the early 2000s with their IA-64 design, or no,
IA-32, I guess it was. I think it's IA32. What happened was it
didn't really get adopted much widely, and AMD made
something that they called, I think, X64 or something like
this. I mean, x86, I guess. Yeah. Because all these Intel
chips, they all became known as x86. The original floating
point was x87, 8087, and then the 87 was absorbed into the
x86. and Pentium is part of the x86 sequence. And then AMD was
making these x86, and they went to the 64-bit processor,
which refers to the, not to the floating point, but to the way
the memory is organized with 64 bits. And then so the AMD x86
design got adopted widely, and even Intel eventually
switched to that. So that's kind of a long-winded answer to
your question, I think. Yeah, but as always, I learned a lot,
so thanks a lot. I think that we should wrap it up because it's
almost an hour, or maybe just even more than an hour right
now. Yeah, thanks a lot. I learned a lot, really. I had a great
laugh. And I think that our audience will enjoy it as much as I
do. That's so great. I'm so delighted to hear it. And the
second edition will be out there before too long. Yeah, I
will put any links that you'll send me into the description. And
thanks a lot for answering all my questions, going deep into
the history and into the technical parts. It's really
awesome. It was really a pleasure.