Welcome to my channel, Alex. Can you please introduce yourself? It's great to be here. Yeah, I'm Alex.
My day job currently is working at Astral, where I work on the linter ruff. And in my spare
time, I do a lot of open source stuff in the Python community. So I'm a CPython core dev. I'm a
typeshed maintainer. I also maintain the typing focused linter flake8-pyi, and I make triage
with MyPy. And I maintain typing_extensions as well. Oh, very, very good list. I'm happy that
you accepted this invitation and I'm going to ask you about some deep typeshed stuff. And I
really want to know, are there any things that we can really improve in the typeshed testing?
Because right now there are a lot of checks, a lot of CI jobs. We check mostly everything that we
can. What can we do better? What's your opinion? That's a really interesting question. I think,
yeah, we already have a lot of tests that make sure that the annotations that we do have are good
and that the stubs that we have are consistent with the runtime. I think probably the thing I
would want to improve on is better stub generation. so that it's easier for people to just add
baseline stubs, which have a decent quality, and they don't have to work really hard to get that.
We have stub generation scripts, and they will produce very basic stubs, but those stubs aren't
really worth much. There are easy ways that we can make them better, and we've got some
contributors at MyPy that are working on stubgen quite a lot at the moment, which is great to see,
but there's still so much more that we can do there, I think. So that's where I would probably
focus efforts right now. I also think that we don't have any side jobs on non-Linux, non-MacOS,
or non-Windows. We only have three operating systems here. And I think it might be a very good
idea to run something like Solitis or something like that. Yeah. Yeah, it's interesting. I
don't know that we've had many people complain about the quality of type checking on Solaris,
for example. But if that's a, so I don't know how much of a problem that is. But if it is a problem,
then I would definitely, definitely be in favor of that. Yeah, I'd be interested in talking to
Solaris folks and seeing what their Yeah, I think that not a lot of people use Solaris, so we don't
have a lot of complaints there, because you have to not only use Solaris and CPython type check,
and you also have to use some specific APIs for that, so you can see the actual problems. But yeah,
that's my point that I really want to see improved from time to time. Okay, I think that this
question is not really related to typeshed, but I cannot simply skip it because I think it will be
very interesting for my audience and for me as well. How do you find Rust and its type system
compared to CPython? I've been enjoying it a lot. The last few days I've been refactoring a lot of
tests, and it is a pain that you have to make every test compile before you can run a single one.
That part I'm not enjoying so much. I think the thing that I studied learning Rust relatively
recently in December, and the thing that surprised me most was that I was expecting it to be
stricter than Python's type system in every way. And in reality, that wasn't the case. There's
some things that you can do in Rust that you can't do in Python. For example, it's much easier to
redefine a symbol to a different type later in the same function in Rust than it is in Python. Mypy
typically won't let you do that. Pirate will never let you do that. So that took me by surprise.
And the reason for that is that Rust scoping rules are such that it's possible to do that safely in
Rust, whereas you couldn't do that safely in Python. But yeah, no, I'm loving writing Rust. It's
very refreshing. I think it's very refreshing. Because when you write in Rust, you compose
programs, you don't just write them. You have to think everything through. You have to think
about memory management, you have to think about exceptions. I mean, the lack of exceptions.
It's very interesting. Yeah, I understand that. Okay. So if we're talking about type systems
and their difference in different languages, what do you think about what are the biggest
challenges for Python type system right now? I think we're at an interesting point in the type
systems development. Over the last, you know, since PEP 484, which was the PEP that introduced
the type system, was introduced, we've had a lot of new features introduced in pretty much every
Python release. So it's been a period of really rapid evolution. And right now, over the past
year, we've seen the creation of the Typing Council and the creation of the first version of the
Typing Swag. And I think... Can you please elaborate a little more on that? Because I'm pretty
sure that a lot of people are not familiar with that. Thanks, yeah. So the Typing Council is a new
body that's been set up, which has several type checker authors represented in it, and several
other people who have been heavily involved in the typing system for the last few years. They
serve as an advisory body to the Steering Council, essentially, where the Steering Council
delegates many decisions on PEPs to them. I think delegate might not be quite the right word
because the Steering Council does have the final say, but it heavily takes their advice on
board. So there has been a new specification for the typing system written up. So that's an
attempt to formally describe how all of the rules that have been created through the various
Python Enhancement Proposals over the last few years, how they all fit together, how they
should work in tandem. And any small minor changes to the typing spec can be automatically
approved by the Typing Council without having to have a new PEP being written. So that's the
other role that the Typing Council has, other than giving their feedback on PEPs. I think the
overall mood in the typing community. So my sense is that at the moment, I can't speak for
everybody in the typing community, but my sense is that the overall mood right now is that we want
to slow down with features a little bit and more formally figure out exactly how they should, how
the existing features that we have should work together and interoperate a bit more. Now, I
think that typing console is doing a great job because the amount of information they have to
collect and to approve with different type checkers and to standardize is just... Very huge.
And I also want to highlight that they don't just create a specification for that. They also
create a compliance suite for all the type checkers. So all the type checkers can have a baseline
of features that should be supported and should be treated the same way. I think that it was a
long-awaited addition to the Python governance team. So very appreciate their work. I
completely agree. Can you please share a bit of maybe a personal history? How did you start
contributing to typeshed? So it might be a good example for others who just want to start
contributing or just for someone who is not aware that they can contribute to typeshed right
now. To go back a bit further, I originally started learning about Python typing because I was
fairly new to Python, really, and I was using PyCharm. PyCharm's type checker was on by default,
so I kept on writing code and I kept on up with these weird, annoying errors about how I said that
this was a list and now it's a dict and PyCharm was getting very angry at me. So I read up on loads of
tutorials and I guess when I learn about something, I like to learn about it properly. So I
learned quite a lot about the Python typing system as a result of that, and then quickly found out
Answering questions on Python typing was a really good way to get lots of points on Stack
Overflow because there were loads of questions on Stack Overflow about Python typing. So
carried on building up my Python typing expertise because of that. And then eventually I was
just reading through the type shed subs for built-ins one day and noticed that a bunch of
parameters weren't marked as positional-only in the stubs when they were. Oh yeah. Yeah. By the
way, did we fix all the param positional-only problems? All that can be detected automatically
using stochastic. Yeah. So I filed a PR, like making some parameters and some methods on
built-in stock property positional-only. And it was merged at like five minutes, I think. I was
like, wow, that was fun. Let's do that again. That was how I got my start. Quickly discovered that
it was really fun working with the team and that the team was incredibly welcoming. I owe a lot to
the other typeshed maintainers because those were some of the first open source contributions
I made. I can completely agree because the typeshed team is amazing. They're very fast to
respond. They're very picky in a good way. They find a lot of different details and different
thing to prove. And I think that it is a very rare example of a project that it is very addictive
contributing to. Yes. Yeah, definitely. So my advice for starting to contribute is to, we're
still adding stubs for things that were added or changed in Python 3.13. So I have an issue open on
typeshed that I wrote up during the PyCon sprints, add or change things that were added or
changed in Python 3.13 to our stubs. So that's a great way you can help us out right now. Yeah,
another way you can help us out is we have a lot of our standard library stubs generally have
fairly complete annotations. But for our third party stubs, there's loads of parameters which
don't have any annotations. or are marked with incomplete, which means it's an alias for any,
but it means that we don't know exactly what should go there yet because we haven't looked into it
yet. So if you fancy going through our stubs and helping improve our third party stubs, those are
also very welcome. I have a very specific workflow for finding stops that you can help with. You
can just press go to type definition and you can find the stops right in front of you in your IDE. So
you can see what stops are filled with annotations and what stops are missing right now. This is
really helpful. So please consider doing that. I would definitely encourage just very small
PRs, five or 10 lines are very welcome. They're very easy for us to review and we'll probably
review them very quickly. If it's a PR of 1000 lines, then we'll get to it eventually, but it might
take a while for us to to look at it because we're quite busy people. Yeah, don't be afraid to just
make very piecemeal contributions. There's just as good as larger contributions, and there's
no shame in that small PR. TypeShift is very beginner-friendly. It is very easy to contribute,
and I highly promote doing so. Yeah, I completely agree. I think my first PR was like five lines or
so changed, and so were around my first 30 PRs. Yeah. I also have one more question that arised just
now, because there are two type systems actually. One is for static checks and one is for Python
runtime. And I think that we've missed the runtime part. Do you have some insights about what
steps are going to land in this part? What are the problems right now that we can solve in the
future? And what are the problems that we cannot solve at all? Sure. Are you interested in Python
3.13 or 14? I think we can discuss both of them. Okay. Python 3.13 is a really exciting release
because we have both an experimental mode where you can turn off the GIL at runtime, which is the
global interpreter lock, which prevents more than one thread running simultaneously in
Python. And we also have another experimental mode, which creates a just-in-time
interpreter. And you can also enable both at once if you want, although they've been created by
different people and different teams, but they do somehow work together nonetheless. So both
of those are unlikely to make your code much faster right now. The version of Python without the
GIL has quite a few optimizations turned off because they're not thread safe yet. And the
just-in-time interpreter for the other experimental build option is very new and doesn't slow
Python down at all, but also doesn't speed it up yet. So for both of them, you'll probably have to
wait until Python 3.14 until they speed up your code much, but you can play around with them now.
And that's exciting things coming for Python 3.14, which is not the next Python release, but the
one after that. We'll hopefully have big speed ups for both single-threaded and
multi-threaded code. In Python 3.14, so not the Python release that's coming out in October,
but the one that will be coming out in 2025, I suppose, we will hopefully be getting PEP 649,
which is lazily evaluated annotations by default in Python. So currently, if you have a
function that returns a class, and then you define that class later on in the same file, or it's a
method on that class that returns itself, then you'll get a name error if you try to reference
that class that doesn't yet exist in the return type of that function or method. And you can get
around that at the moment by doing from done to future import annotations at the top of your file.
But the problem with that is that it turns every annotation in your file into a string. So this
breaks tools that do runtime introspection of annotations Uh, like the TypeGuard library or
TriCast or Pydantic or FastAPI. Uh, and these tools have become really popular for the last few
years. So originally the plan was from, for, from future import annotations to become the
default in Python 3.10. But then that plan was scrapped, uh, because it was realized that it
would break all of these tools. So the new plan is to, uh, have. all annotations be runtime
objects, just like they are now, but for those two runtime objects to be lazily evaluated on
request using descriptors. This is quite a complicated change to implement, which involves
lots of changes to the compiler and to the Python data model, but it should hopefully solve all
use cases. It is currently halfway towards being implemented in CPython at the moment and
should be landing in Python 3.14. And the work is being done by Jelle Zijlstra. I hope I
pronounced his name correctly. Yeah, I think so. I think so. But I learned several times how to
pronounce his name correctly. So yeah. Yeah. So he's the other typing module maintainer at
CPython, and also a typeshed maintainer, and black developer, and MyPy maintainer, and
typing_extensions maintainer. So he also does a lot of things. He does a lot of things. He is very
active in both the Python core development and in typeshed and in typing_extensions because I
think that he is the main maintainer of type extensions as far as I remember. Do you have any other
examples of things that will be better in future versions of Python considering runtime
support of types? So for introspection, maybe some changes to inspect modules, something like
that. Oh, inspect.signatures. Has that been implemented? It's a work in progress. Right. Yeah.
So there's currently a proposal by Serhiy Storchaka, again, I hope I pronounced his name
correctly, to implement support for functions, better support for functions that have
multiple signatures in Python. So we already support these in the static typing system via
typing.overload. But at runtime, if you call inspect.signature on a function, then it will
only ever give you one signature for that function. And that's often not very accurate if you
have something like a function that's decorated with functools.singleDispatch, for
example. or just a built-in function like max or min, which you can use in many different ways. If
it's implemented, then this proposal will mean that I can't remember whether the proposal was
for it to return a multi-signature object or a list of signature objects. It's quite a
complicated thing to work through exactly how it would work. Yeah. So we'll see whether that
happens, but fingers crossed. I think it would definitely better reflect Python semantics at
runtime. I really hope that Python will get better at both static checks and at runtime checks
because both are very important for the ecosystem and for Python developers. Typing is really
interesting and I highly recommend everyone to at least try to contribute to typeshed and maybe
some other tools like pyright, MyPy and CPython itself. Alex, thanks a lot for coming and
answering my questions. I think that our audience will have a lot to learn from your expertise
and from your interview. And it was a pleasure for me to see you here. So thanks. Thanks so much for
inviting me. This is really fun.